A Guide to the Silas Chandler Letters, 1862-1865
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Silas Chandler Letters, 1862-1865
The Library of Virginia
23984a
32 leaves, negative photostats
Silas Chandler
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying, 29 May 1953, by Charles A. Taylor of Urbanna, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Born in 1830 in York County, Virginia, to James E. and Eliza A. White Chandler, Silas Chandler moved to Middlesex County, Virginia. When the Civil War began, he enlisted in Company B, 55th Virginia Infantry. Company B later was detached and made into Fleet's Artillery Company. He was wounded at Antietam, and later taken prisoner there. Exchanged, he fought at Chancellorsville and at Gettysburg, where he again was wounded. Chandler's unit was later sent to Tennessee, where it arrived just after the battle of Chickamauga. Chandler returned to the Army of Northern Virginia, and served through the siege of Petersburg and surrendered at Appomattox Court House. After the war, Chandler returned to Middlesex County where he was a farmer and an oysterman. He married Ann Elizabeth Gayle (1837-by 1880) 28 December 1852 and they had 8 children. He married Mary C. Gayle (1842-1913) 11 January 1881. Chandler died April 1912.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1862-1865, of Silas Chandler (1830-1912) of Middlesex County, Virginia, and Fleet's Artillery Company, to his wife Ann Elizabeth Gayle Chandler (1837-by 1880) discussing camp life and combat, and requesting she write. Chandler comments on the reorganization of the army; the Peninsular Campaign; the battle of Chancellorsville; the possible evacuation of Virginia by the army; his unit's joining the Army of Tennessee; the battle of Chickamagua; the siege of Petersburg, including the battle of the Crater; Confederate maneuvers in Tennessee; the Hampton Roads Peace Conference; desertions; and the proposal to draft African Americans into the Confederate Army.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
John J. Chandler, Letters, 1863-1864 (LVA accession 23984b).
Contents List
- Letter, 31 March 1862, discussing camp life and the anticipated movement of the unit.
- Letter, 2 May 1862, detailing the army's preparation for meeting the enemy and asking his wife to write.
- Letter, 20 June 1862, concerning army reorganization and the fighting which occurred during the Peninsular Campaign.
- Letter, 7 May 1863, concerning the battle of Chancellorsville and how he is faring.
- Letter, 5 August 1863, reporting a rumor that the army might evacuate from Virginia and asking his wife to write to him and send him socks.
- Letter, 30 August 1863, thanking his wife for the letter she wrote and sending camp news.
- Letter, 23 September 1863, written from Atlanta, Georgia, informing his wife of the unit's trip from Virginia to Georgia en route to joining the Army of Tennessee.
- Letter, 3 October 1863, hoping that his wife and family are doing well and informing her of the battle of Chickamauga.
- Letter, 9 July 1864, written from Petersburg, where a siege has begun, informing his wife of conditions there and stating that he believes the Union army under Grant will be defeated and the war will end, and also containing personal news.
- Letter, 31 July 1864, describing the battle of the Crater in Petersburg, also hoping his wife and family are doing well.
- Letter, 17 August 1864, informing his wife that he is well and hopes she and the family are also, and also describing a fight with the Union army north of the James River.
- Letter, 29 August 1864, detailing a battle with Union troops along the Petersburg lines and sending personal news.
- Letter, 2 November 1864, containing news about fighting along the lines in Petersburg and about Hood's move into Tennessee, and personal news.
- Letter, 12 November 1864, hoping the children are well and stating he hopes to get a furlough to come home for a visit.
- Letter, 25 January 1865, discussing the Hampton Roads Peace Conference, rumors of evacuating Virginia, and the rise of desertions.
- Letter, 28 January 1865, containing personal news.
- Letter, 21 February 1865, discussing desertions and the proposed drafting of African-Americans for service in the Confederate army.